<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<pdf_text>Citation: Al-Rabiah, A.A.; Alkathiri,
R.R.; Bagabas, A.A. Process
Development for Methyl Isobutyl
Ketone Production Using the
Low-Pressure One-Step Gas-Phase
Selective Hydrogenation of Acetone.
Processes 2022, 10, 1992. https://
doi.org/10.3390/pr10101992
Academic Editor: Jean-Claude Assaf
Received: 1 September 2022
Accepted: 27 September 2022
Published: 2 October 2022
Publisher’s Note: MDPI stays neutral
with regard to jurisdictional claims in
published maps and institutional afﬁl-
iations.
Copyright:
© 2022 by the authors.
Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland.
This article is an open access article
distributed
under
the
terms
and
conditions of the Creative Commons
Attribution (CC BY) license (https://
creativecommons.org/licenses/by/
4.0/).
processes
Article
Process Development for Methyl Isobutyl Ketone Production
Using the Low-Pressure One-Step Gas-Phase Selective
Hydrogenation of Acetone
Abdulrahman A. Al-Rabiah 1,*
, Raed R. Alkathiri 1 and Abdulaziz A. Bagabas 2
1
Chemical Engineering Department, King Saud University, P.O. Box 800, Riyadh 11421, Saudi Arabia
2
National Petrochemical Technology Center (NPTC), King Abdulaziz City for Science and
Technology (KACST), P.O. Box 6086, Riyadh 11442, Saudi Arabia
*
Correspondence: arabiah@ksu.edu.sa; Tel.: +966-11-4676844; Fax: +966-11-4678770
Abstract: Methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) is a highly valuable product in the chemical industry. It is
widely used as an extracting agent for heavy metals, antibiotics, and lubricating oils. Generally, MIBK
can be produced by three-step and one-step liquid-phase methods. These methods are expensive
and energy-demanding due to the high pressure and low conversion of acetone. A novel nano-
Pd/nano-ZnCr2O4 catalyst was developed to produce MIBK with high conversion and selectivity
of 77.3% and 72.1%, respectively, at 350 ◦C and ambient pressure, eliminating the need for high
pressure in conventional MIBK processes. This study is the ﬁrst that proposes a newly developed
process of methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) production using the low-pressure one-step gas-phase
selective hydrogenation of acetone. In this work, a novel process ﬂow diagram has been developed
for the production of MIBK using the developed nano-catalyst. The process was heat integrated,
resulting in a 26% and a 19.5% reduction in the heating and cooling utilities, respectively, leading to
a 12.6% reduction in the total energy demand. An economic analysis was performed to determine
the economic feasibility of the developed process, which shows that the process is highly proﬁtable,
in which it reduced both the capital and operating costs of MIBK synthesis and showed a return on
investment (ROI) of 29.6% with a payback period of 2.2 years. It was found that the ROI could be
increased by 18% when the reactor temperature is increased to 350 ◦C. In addition, the economic
sensitivity analysis showed that the process is highly sensitive to product prices and least sensitive to
utility prices, which is due to the versatility of the process that requires only a low amount of energy.
Keywords: methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK); acetone self-condensation; selective hydrogenation;
process development; heat integration; economic analysis; nano-Pd/nano-ZnCr2O4 catalyst
1. Introduction
Methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) is an industrially important chemical worldwide. It can
be used in a wide variety of important applications, including protective surface coating,
vinyl, and acrylic resins, the extraction of metallic salts, and the removal of parafﬁn from
mineral oils [1–5]. It is also used in the production of paints and rubber, as well as a solvent
in a variety of pharmaceuticals and adhesives [6,7].
The global production of MIBK was 430,000 metric tons in 2020 [8]. The market
for MIBK is expected to grow at a compound annual growth rate (CAGR) of more than
6% by 2026. This is due to the increasing demand for MIBK, especially in the synthesis
of antioxidant additives for rubber, and the growing demand for solvents in chemical
processes [9].
In addition to MIBK, a crucial byproduct is also produced, which is isopropyl alcohol
(IPA). It has tremendous industrial, medical, and hygienic applications, including alcohol
wipes, hand sanitizers, disinfectants, and swabs, which increases the prospects of applying
the MIBK process with minimal waste. According to the Centers for Disease Control and
Processes 2022, 10, 1992. https://doi.org/10.3390/pr10101992
https://www.mdpi.com/journal/processes
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
2 of 14
Prevention (CDC) in the United States, alcohol-based hand sanitizers and cleansing wipes
contain between 60% and 90% of alcohol, and the use of 70% of IPA is recommended [10].
Medical IPA was scientiﬁcally proven as a disinfectant that inactivates viruses such as the
COVID-19 virus.
MIBK can be produced by several processes, but essentially by a three-step [11] method
and a single-step method [12–17]. Each of these processes can be carried out with different
catalysts, raw materials, and reaction conditions [12]. The three-step method involves aldol
condensation of acetone over homogeneous aqueous-based catalysts, such as sodium and
calcium hydroxide, forming diacetone alcohol (DAA), which is subsequently dehydrated
to mesityl oxide (MO). The ﬁnal step is the selective hydrogenation of the C=C bond of MO
to MIBK using Cu or Ni catalysts [18,19]. The most commonly occurring side reactions are
over-condensation and unselective hydrogenation [20].
The three-step process produces a considerable amount of wastewater containing
acidic impurities due to the homogeneous catalyst, which creates a corrosive environment
associated with high capital and operating costs for the neutralization process, acetone
condensation, and product puriﬁcation [18,19,21]. Alternatively, the one-step process
using a metal-supported catalyst was demonstrated to be more efﬁcient [22–28]. The
support catalyzes acetone condensation to mesityl oxide (MO), an α,β-unsaturated ketone,
followed by in situ catalytic reductions to MIBK using palladium on acidic ion-exchange
resins [18,29,30], while there are other processes that use Pd/zirconium phosphate [31].
In the one-step liquid-phase process, hydrogen and acetone are passed over metal base
catalysts at moderate temperature and high pressure to produce MIBK in a single step,
saving enormous costs that are required in the three-step method [32]. Under these reaction
conditions, aldol condensation and dehydration are reversible [33], but the catalyst shifts
the equilibrium toward MO, irreversibly hydrogenating it toward MIBK [28].
Despite the many advantages offered by the liquid-phase one-step process, it suffers
from high pressure, ranging from 3 to 10 MPa [13], which signiﬁcantly increases the capital
and operating costs. This is in addition to the large recycle ﬂow rate due to the low
conversion of acetone, which increases the size of equipment in the recycle loop as well as
the additional energy that is needed for recovering the unreacted acetone in the distillation
column. Therefore, it is an industrial objective to reduce the pressure and increase the
conversion and selectivity to make the process more proﬁtable.
Recently, Qianling et al. reported a bifunctional catalyst TiO2/Al2O32 and Pd/Cor for
one-pot liquid-phase synthesis of MIBK from acetone, which provides acetone conversion
of (35–45)% with a selectivity of (80–90)% to MIBK at 150 ◦C and 2.0 MPa [34]. However, the
process still suffers from the high-pressure requirement with moderate acetone conversion.
Baining et al. proposed an alternative support with high thermal stability and adjustable
acid-base property using phosphor-doped h-BN that catalyzes the aldol condensation
and dehydration to provide an acetone conversion of 58.24% and selectivity of 68.39%
to MIBK [35]. In addition, various kinds of support, including metal oxides [19,36,37]
and sulfonated graphene [38,39], have also been a prime focus in the development of the
process.
In this context, a novel nanocrystalline zinc chromite-supported nanopalladium (nano-
Pd/nano-ZnCr2O4) catalyst was developed by Bagabas et al. and Al-Rabiah et al. [20,40,41],
which enables the production of MIBK in a one-step gas-phase reaction at atmospheric
pressure. This can overcome the inﬁrmities that the conventional process suffers from.
However, the process requires a temperature of (200–350) ◦C, which is higher than the
conventional process, which uses a temperature of (120–160) ◦C [15].
The reaction involves base–acid coupling of acetone to form mesityl oxide (MO),
followed by its hydrogenation to methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK). The products with this
catalyst are methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) as the main product, isopropyl alcohol (IPA) as
the main byproduct, and diiasobutyl ketone (DIBK), mesityl oxide (MO), and mesitylene
(M) are also formed [20,40,41]. The MIBK produced by low-pressure one-step gas-phase
acetone condensation has an acetone conversion of (20–78)% and MIBK selectivities of
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
3 of 14
(40–73)% for reaction temperatures of 200–350 ◦C with a hydrogen-acetone molar feed ratio
of 1 to 6 [20,40,41].
This research work focuses on the development of a novel process for the production
of methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) from hydrogen and acetone in a one-step gas-phase
reaction at ambient pressure using a novel nano-Pd/nano-ZnCr2O4 catalyst. Heat inte-
gration is conducted to reduce the process utilities. In addition, this work investigates
process economics to measure the proﬁtability and the impact of market volatility on the
proﬁtability of the process.
2. MIBK Process Development
The developed process ﬂow diagram for the production of methyl isobutyl ketone is
shown in Figure 1. A process simulation was conducted using CHEMCAD v.7.1 software
based on a production of 30,000 metric tons of MIBK per annum with 30 days assigned for
maintenance. The thermodynamic model chosen was UNIFAC as a cubic equation of state.
The reactor conversion, selectivity, and feed ratio used in the simulation were based on the
aforementioned experiment.
 
 
catalyst are methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) as the main product, isopropyl alcohol (IPA) 
as the main byproduct, and diiasobutyl ketone (DIBK), mesityl oxide (MO), and mesity-
lene (M) are also formed as byproducts [20,40,41]. The MIBK produced by low-pressure 
one-step gas-phase acetone condensation has an acetone conversion of (20–78)% and 
MIBK selectivities of (40–73)% for reaction temperatures of 200–350 °C with a hydrogen-
acetone molar feed ratio of 1 to 6 [20,40,41].  
This research work focuses on the development of a novel process for the production 
of methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) from hydrogen and acetone in a one-step gas-phase 
reaction at ambient pressure using a novel nano-Pd/nano-ZnCr2O4 catalyst. Heat integra-
tion is conducted to reduce the process utilities. In addition, this work investigates process 
economics to measure the profitability and the impact of market volatility on the profita-
bility of the process. 
2. MIBK Process Development  
The developed process flow diagram for the production of methyl isobutyl ketone is 
shown in Figure 1. A process simulation was conducted using CHEMCAD v.7.1 software 
based on a production of 30,000 metric tons of MIBK per annum with 30 days assigned 
for maintenance. The thermodynamic model chosen was UNIFAC as a cubic equation of 
state. The reactor conversion, selectivity, and feed ratio used in the simulation were based 
on the aforementioned experiment.  
 
Figure 1. Developed process flow diagram (PFD) of the MIBK process. 
The fresh acetone feed (stream 1) enters the process at 70 °C and 1.8 atm in a liquid 
phase and is mixed with the recycled acetone (stream 14), which enters at 74 °C and 1.8 
atm. Before entering the reactor R-101, the mixed stream is heated to 300 °C. The hydrogen 
feed is mixed with recycled hydrogen (stream 11) before being heated to 300 °C and fed 
into reactor R-101. Both reactor feeds pass through valves, V-101 and V-102, to reduce the 
pressure in the reactor. The hydrogen–acetone molar feed ratio is maintained at 2:1, as 
recommended [40,41]. The reaction proceeds isothermally in the gas phase at 300 °C and 
1 atm in a fixed bed catalytic reactor (R-101). The conversion of acetone is 66%, with a 
selectivity of 69.4% to methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK). Other products, such as isopropa-
nol (IPA) and diiasobutyl ketone (DIBK), are also produced. The selectivity of each of 
these substances was determined based on the experimental work, which is shown in Ta-
ble 1. The reactor effluent will then be compressed to 6.5 atm to compensate for pressure 
losses through the pipelines and to enhance the separation of hydrogen without major 
product losses from the process stream at low pressure and high temperature, preventing 
the use of cryogenic conditions. MIBK losses at 1 atm are approximately 6 kmol/h. Conse-
quently, compression is mandatory to avoid cryogenic conditions. At 6.5 atm, the losses 
drop to about 0.7 kmol/h of MIBK. After compression, the stream is cooled to 35 °C in E-
Figure 1. Developed process ﬂow diagram (PFD) of the MIBK process.
The fresh acetone feed (stream 1) enters the process at 70 ◦C and 1.8 atm in a liquid
phase and is mixed with the recycled acetone (stream 14), which enters at 74 ◦C and 1.8 atm.
Before entering the reactor R-101, the mixed stream is heated to 300 ◦C. The hydrogen
feed is mixed with recycled hydrogen (stream 11) before being heated to 300 ◦C and fed
into reactor R-101. Both reactor feeds pass through valves, V-101 and V-102, to reduce the
pressure in the reactor. The hydrogen–acetone molar feed ratio is maintained at 2:1, as
recommended [40,41]. The reaction proceeds isothermally in the gas phase at 300 ◦C and
1 atm in a ﬁxed bed catalytic reactor (R-101). The conversion of acetone is 66%, with a
selectivity of 69.4% to methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK). Other products, such as isopropanol
(IPA) and diiasobutyl ketone (DIBK), are also produced. The selectivity of each of these
substances was determined based on the experimental work, which is shown in Table 1.
The reactor efﬂuent will then be compressed to 6.5 atm to compensate for pressure losses
through the pipelines and to enhance the separation of hydrogen without major product
losses from the process stream at low pressure and high temperature, preventing the use of
cryogenic conditions. MIBK losses at 1 atm are approximately 6 kmol/h. Consequently,
compression is mandatory to avoid cryogenic conditions. At 6.5 atm, the losses drop to
about 0.7 kmol/h of MIBK. After compression, the stream is cooled to 35 ◦C in E-103
before being fed into the ﬂash drum F-101. The overhead stream from ﬂash drum F-101
contains nearly 99.996% of the unreacted hydrogen, which is recycled and mixed with the
fresh hydrogen. The bottom stream from ﬂash drum F-101 (stream 12) is then throttled to
1.8 atm in V-103 before entering the distillation column, T-101. Nearly 99% of the unreacted
acetone is recovered in the overhead stream of T-101, using 48 stages, before being mixed
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
4 of 14
with the fresh acetone. The acetone/water system forms an azeotropic mixture at higher
compositions; therefore, about 0.04 of the entered water into the column is recovered into
the top stream to maintain the mixture in the column below the azeotropic point. The
bottom stream from T-101 is cooled to 70 ◦C in E-106 before being sent to a water decanter,
D-101, where 90% of the water is removed. The second outlet stream from the decanter
enters the distillation column, T-102, which consists of 34 stages, where 99.28% of the
isopropanol (IPA) is recovered. The remaining water is also separated with IPA in the
distillate stream, and the mixture is then cooled to 40 ◦C in E-109. The purity of IPA in the
top stream of T-102 is almost 68%, which is highly recommended to be used as sanitizer
in the medical industry, and therefore, there is no need to install a further distillation
column for increasing the purity of the IPA. The bottom stream from T-102 enters another
distillation column, T-103, which consists of 67 stages where 99% of the MIBK is recovered
in the overhead stream with a purity of 99.83 wt.%, achieving the product speciﬁcations [14].
The MIBK stream is then cooled to 40 ◦C in E-110 before being sent to the storage tank. The
bottom stream from T-103, which contains the heavy components (e.g., DAA, MO, M, and
DIBK), is cooled to 40 ◦C in E-111.
Table 1. The conversion and selectivity of the MIBK process at different temperatures [20,40,41].
Temperature
(◦C)
Acetone
Conversion%
Selectivity
MIBK
DIBK
MO
M
IPA
DA &amp; Others
200
20.1
40.6
10.2
6.1
2.1
40.7
0.3
250
40.7
53.9
12.3
4.4
2.5
25.8
1.1
300
66
69.4
12.4
2.1
2.6
11.2
2.3
350
77.3
72.1
13.5
2.2
2.7
5.4
4.1
3. Heat Integration in the MIBK Process
Heat integration is an essential part of the process development. The reduction
in energy usage not only reduces the operating costs but also prevents harmful carbon
emissions in the environment. The required heating and cooling utilities were identiﬁed
for the process as shown in Figure 1. Each process stream was drawn with a tail and a
head representing the supplied temperature and the target temperature, respectively. The
ﬁnal heat exchanger network is shown in Figure 2, where the red and blue lines denote the
hot and cold streams, respectively. The constructed network utilizes the energy content
and high temperature of the reactor efﬂuent to heat up the feed streams. The acetone feed
(stream 2) leaving mixer M-101 will ﬁrst be heated by the reactor efﬂuent from 74.3 ◦C to
242 ◦C, in which no further heating can occur due to the process constraint prohibiting
phase change before the inlet of the compressor. The reactor efﬂuent will be further cooled
by the hydrogen feed (stream 5) until it reaches a minimum temperature approach of
10 ◦C to avoid an excessive large area. The outcome of the heat integration, as shown in
Figure 3, is a reduction in the heating and cooling utilities by 26% and 19.5%, respectively.
The reduction in the total utility demand is about 12.6%. In terms of economics, the
implemented heat integration has resulted in an increase in the annualized capital cost
by $12,134/year (for 10 years of operation). However, operating costs have decreased by
$611,852/year, indicating a highly plausible energy utilization that satisﬁes both technical
and economic aspects.
The blue columns in Figure 3 represent the utility demand before the heat integration,
while the green columns represent the current value of the utility demand in the MIBK
process after heat integration. In addition, the ﬁgure is divided into three sections, starting
from the total utility demand, including the combined heating and cooling utilities, then
the heating utility in the middle, while the cooling utility is placed on the right side. The
process was re-simulated after the heat integration using CHEMCAD v.7.1. The developed
ﬂowsheet after heat integration is shown in Figure 4. The material balances for the key
streams of the developed MIBK process are shown in Table 2.
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
5 of 14
Processes 2022, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW 
5 of 14 
 
 
 
Figure 2. Heat exchanger network of the process streams for the developed process. 
 
Figure 3. Heat integration outcome for the developed process. 
The blue columns in Figure 3 represent the utility demand before the heat integration, 
while the green columns represent the current value of the utility demand in the MIBK 
process after heat integration. In addition, the figure is divided into three sections, starting 
from the total utility demand, including the combined heating and cooling utilities, then 
the heating utility in the middle, while the cooling utility is placed on the right side. The 
process was re-simulated after the heat integration using CHEMCAD v.7.1. The devel-
oped flowsheet after heat integration is shown in Figure 4. The material balances for the 
key streams of the developed MIBK process are shown in Table 2. 
Figure 2. Heat exchanger network of the process streams for the developed process.
Processes 2022, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW 
5 of 14 
 
 
 
Figure 2. Heat exchanger network of the process streams for the developed process. 
 
Figure 3. Heat integration outcome for the developed process. 
The blue columns in Figure 3 represent the utility demand before the heat integration, 
while the green columns represent the current value of the utility demand in the MIBK 
process after heat integration. In addition, the figure is divided into three sections, starting 
from the total utility demand, including the combined heating and cooling utilities, then 
the heating utility in the middle, while the cooling utility is placed on the right side. The 
process was re-simulated after the heat integration using CHEMCAD v.7.1. The devel-
oped flowsheet after heat integration is shown in Figure 4. The material balances for the 
key streams of the developed MIBK process are shown in Table 2. 
Figure 3. Heat integration outcome for the developed process.
Processes 2022, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW 
6 of 14 
 
 
Figure 4. Developed process flow diagram (PFD) of the MIBK process after heat integration. 
Table 2. Material balance of key streams for the developed MIBK process. 
Streams 
Acetone 
Mixed 
Feed 
(S-2) 
Hydrogen 
Mixed 
Feed 
(S-16) 
Reactor 
Effluent 
(S-6) 
Acetone 
Recycle 
(S-19) 
Hydrogen 
Recycle 
(S-14) 
Waste-
Water  
(S-22) 
(IPA+Water) 
Product 
(S-25) 
MIBK 
Product 
(S-28) 
(DIBK, 
DAA, 
MO, M) 
Product 
(S-30) 
Temperature (°C) 
74.29 
34.74 
300 
61.49 
35 
70 
40 
40 
40 
Figure 4. Developed process ﬂow diagram (PFD) of the MIBK process after heat integration.
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
6 of 14
Table 2. Material balance of key streams for the developed MIBK process.
Streams
Acetone
Mixed Feed
(S-2)
Hydrogen
Mixed Feed
(S-16)
Reactor
Efﬂuent
(S-6)
Acetone
Recycle
(S-19)
Hydrogen
Recycle
(S-14)
Waste-Water
(S-22)
(IPA +
Water)
Product
(S-25)
MIBK
Product
(S-28)
(DIBK,
DAA, MO,
M) Product
(S-30)
Temperature
(◦C)
74.29
34.74
300
61.49
35
70
40
40
40
Pressure
(atm)
1.8
5.9
1
1.8
5.9
1.4
1.4
1.9
2.4
Enthalpy
(MJ/h)
−37,473.6
−2720.4
−35,506.3
−10,788
−2695.83
−12,968.1
−5515
−12,209.8
−3039.6
Molar vapor
fraction
0.29
1
1
1
1
0
0
0
0
Molar ﬂow
rate
(kmol/h)
160.11
342.63
443.12
50.13
283.34
45.94
18.02
37.46
8.25
Mass ﬂow
rate (kg/h)
9224.8
1266.14
10,491
2837.35
1146.63
827.54
−5515
3748.6
1054.04
Component ﬂow rates (kmol/h)
Hydrogen
0.0109
331.31
272
0.0109
272
0
0
0
0
Acetone
158.3
7.64
56.4
48.27
7.64
0
0.49
0
0
MIBK
0
0.75
38.75
0
0.75
0
0.2492
37.37
0.38
Water
1.84
2.36
55.24
1.84
2.36
45.94
5.1
0
0
DAA
0
0.0012
1.26
0
0.0012
0
0
0
1.26
MO
0
0.0115
1.16
0
0.0115
0
0
0.0065
1.15
M
0
0.0148
0.9637
0
0.0148
0
0
0
0.9489
IPA
0.00645
0.5225
12.79
0.0065
0.5225
0
12.18
0.0883
0
DIBK
0
0.0155
4.54
0
0.0155
0
0
0
4.53
4. Economic Analysis
An economic analysis was performed to verify the proﬁtability of the process based
on several economic indicators, including the return on investment, payback period, net
present worth, and discounted cash ﬂow rate of return.
The return on investment (ROI) is expressed on an annual basis, and it is deﬁned as the
average net proﬁt divided by the total ﬁxed capital investment as shown in Equation (1) [42].
ROI =
Yearly net proﬁts
Fixed capital investement
(1)
The payback period (PBP) is deﬁned as the required time to recoup the original
depreciable ﬁxed capital investment as shown in Equation (2) [42].
PBP = Depreciable ﬁxed capital investment
Avg. proﬁt/yr + avg. depreciation/yr
(2)
The net present worth (NPW) is deﬁned as the difference between the present value of
the annual cash ﬂow and the initial required investment as shown in Equation (3).
NPW =
Net cash ﬂow at time t
(1 + interest rate)time of cash ﬂow
(3)
The discounted cash ﬂow rate of return (DCFRR) represents the maximum inter-
est rate that a project can afford to pay for its total capital investment [43] as shown in
Equation (4) [42].
NPW =
n=T
∑
n=1
Cash ﬂow at time t
(1 + DCFRR)n
− Total capital investment = 0
(4)
In order to determine the economic indicators, the following should be calculated:
(i) the cost of the equipment; (ii) the costs of raw materials and utilities; (iii) the total capital
cost; and (iv) the total production cost.
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
7 of 14
4.1. Purchase Cost
In order to determine the purchase costs, the process equipment sizes must ﬁrst be
calculated; the process simulator was used for this purpose. In addition, the costs were
estimated using the CHEMCAD costing package, adjusting all the costs to 2022 using the
Chemical Engineering Plant Cost Index (CEPCI) [44]. Figure 5 depicts the distribution
of the process equipment costs. Note that the condensers and reboilers of the distillation
columns are compiled with heat exchangers. The cost distribution of the process equipment
indicates that the distillation columns account for the largest share of ﬁxed capital costs
of around 40% as the most expensive units of the process, which is due to the byproducts
generated by the process.
 
NPW � � Cash flow at time t
�1 � DCFRR��
� Total capital investment � 0
���
 
(4)
In order to determine the economic indicators, the following should be calculated: (i) 
the cost of the equipment; (ii) the costs of raw materials and utilities; iii) the total capital 
cost; and (iv) the total production cost.  
4.1. Purchase Cost 
In order to determine the purchase costs, the process equipment sizes must first be 
calculated; the process simulator was used for this purpose. In addition, the costs were 
estimated using the CHEMCAD costing package, adjusting all the costs to 2022 using the 
Chemical Engineering Plant Cost Index (CEPCI) [44]. Figure 5 depicts the distribution of 
the process equipment costs. Note that the condensers and reboilers of the distillation col-
umns are compiled with heat exchangers. The cost distribution of the process equipment 
indicates that the distillation columns account for the largest share of fixed capital costs of 
around 40% as the most expensive units of the process, which is due to the byproducts 
generated by the process.  
 
Figure 5. Fixed capital cost distribution for the developed process. 
Figure 5. Fixed capital cost distribution for the developed process.
4.2. Raw Material and Utility Costs
Besides the ﬁxed capital costs, the raw materials and utility costs are major components
of the production cost. The prices of the raw materials, utilities, and products are shown in
Table 3.
Table 3. Cost input for the developed MIBK process [45,46].
Item
Price Unit
Raw Materials
Acetone
$790/ton
Hydrogen
$2500/ton
Utilities
High-pressure steam (hps)
$5.66/GJ
Medium-pressure steam (mps)
$4.77/GJ
Low-pressure steam (lps)
$4.54/GJ
Boiler feed water
$1.532/1000 kg
Cooling water (cw)
$15.7/1000 m3
Electricity
$0.0674/kWh
Products
Methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK)
$2120/ton
Isopropanol (IPA)
$1540/ton
(DAA, DIBK, MO, M)
$1300/ton
The distribution of the utility costs is depicted in Figure 6. It shows that electricity
represents 35% of the total utility cost, which is due to its high prices. Low-pressure
steam is the second most cost-intensive required utility that is used in the reboiler of T-101.
Although cooling water is the most consumed in terms of volume, it accounts for only 5%
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
8 of 14
of the total utility cost, which is due to the low price of cooling water compared to the other
utilities.
 
(DAA, DIBK, MO, M) 
$1300/ton 
The distribution of the utility costs is depicted in Figure 6. It shows that electricity 
represents 35% of the total utility cost, which is due to its high prices. Low-pressure steam 
is the second most cost-intensive required utility that is used in the reboiler of T-101. Alt-
hough cooling water is the most consumed in terms of volume, it accounts for only 5% of 
the total utility cost, which is due to the low price of cooling water compared to the other 
utilities.  
 
Figure 6. Utility cost distribution for the MIBK process. 
4.3. Total Capital Cost 
The total production cost comprises all of the direct, indirect, and general expenses 
[42]. The direct costs are estimated as a fraction of the purchased equipment costs and 
Figure 6. Utility cost distribution for the MIBK process.
4.3. Total Capital Cost
The total production cost comprises all of the direct, indirect, and general expenses [42].
The direct costs are estimated as a fraction of the purchased equipment costs and include
all the prices of the delivery and installation of the purchased equipment, installed instru-
mentation and control systems, installed piping, electrical systems, yard improvement,
buildings, and service facilities [42]. The direct cost of the developed MIBK process is
$18.34 million per annum. The indirect cost was calculated as a fraction of the direct cost
provided in Plant Design and Economics for Chemical Engineers by Peter and Timmer-
haus [42]. It includes the engineering and supervision costs, construction, legal, contractor,
and contingency expenses, which represent $7.34 million [42]. The ﬁxed capital investment
is the summation of the direct and indirect costs [42]; it is $25.68 million for the MIBK
process. The total capital investment is a combination of the ﬁxed capital investment and
the working capital. The working capital was taken as 0.15 of the total capital cost for the
ﬂuid processing plant [42]. The total capital investment in the developed MIBK process is
$30.21 million.
4.4. Total Product Cost
The total product cost represents all of the annual expenses that are required for
production. It includes raw material prices, utility costs, operating labor, maintenance and
repairs, operating supplies, laboratory charges, royalties, taxes, ﬁnancing, insurance, rent,
depreciation, plant overhead, administration, distribution and selling, and research and
development expenses, all of which are fractions of the ﬁxed capital investment provided
by Peter and Timmerhaus [42]. The total production cost, excluding depreciation, for the
developed MIBK process is $55.78 million annually.
4.5. Proﬁtability Evaluation
The process proﬁtability can now be evaluated after obtaining all of the necessary
information. The total raw material cost is $42.71 million per year, which accounts for
76.7% of the total product cost. The total product price is $83.81 million yearly, which
shows a positive proﬁt margin. Therefore, ﬂuctuations in the raw material or product prices
may have a considerable inﬂuence on the process proﬁtability; consequently, a sensitivity
analysis is required for the price ﬂuctuation. The plant has shown its feasibility in being
commercially applied; the return on investment for the plant is 29.6%/y, with a payback
period of 2.2 years. Furthermore, the plant could generate $28.93 million proﬁts in 10 years
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
9 of 14
of operation. The discounted rate of return on investment of the plant is 26.6%. Table 4
summarizes the economic performance of the MIBK process.
Table 4. The economic performance for the developed MIBK process.
Factor
Value
Total Raw Material Cost
$42.71 million/y
Total Utility Cost
$1.646 million/y
Fixed Capital Investment (FCI)
$25.68 million
Total Capital Investment (TCI)
$30.22 million
Depreciation
MACRS, 5 years recovery period
Total Product Cost
$55.78 million/y
Revenue
$83.81 million/y
Return on Investment (ROI)
29.6%/y
Payback Period
2.2 y
Net Present Worth (at i = 15%)
$28.93 million
Discounted Cash Flow Rate of Return (DCFRR)
26.6%
4.6. Economic Sensitivity Analysis
The petrochemical industry is a highly volatile market that has experienced many
ups and downs throughout its market history [47,48]. Therefore, to account for these
perturbations, raw material costs, product costs, utility costs, and ﬁxed capital costs were
varied by ±15% of their current prices. Figure 7 shows the overall sensitivity analysis
of the above factors at a constant production rate and 10 years of operation. It shows
that the process is highly dependent on the product prices, in which a 10% increase could
make the process an extremely lucrative process with an ROI of 54.3%. However, a 15%
decrease could make the process unproﬁtable with an ROI of 4.1%. The ﬂuctuation in the
product prices gave maximum and minimum values of ROI in the sensitivity analysis,
which represents the importance of reducing the MIBK losses throughout the process. On
the other hand, raw material prices come in as a second large contributor to the process
proﬁtability, in which a 15% increase in the raw material prices decreases the ROI to
12.7%, whereas a 15% reduction in the raw material prices increases the ROI to 46%. This
highlights how crucial it is to properly recover unreacted raw materials (e.g., acetone
and hydrogen), in addition to the great inﬂuence that the higher selectivity can have on
the process proﬁtability. The ﬁxed capital investment was found to be the third largest
contributor, with an ROI of 23.5% if its cost increased by 15% and an ROI of 37.7% if
its cost decreased by 15%. This also highlights that even though recovering more of the
product and raw materials can increase the TCI, it has a lower negative inﬂuence on the
process proﬁtability than losing them. In addition, it is worth noting that the utility cost,
as expected, has an insigniﬁcant impact on the ROI as the current utility cost is $1.646
million per year, representing only 2.95% of the total product cost, which is due to the
low-pressure requirement in the process compared to the conventional process, which is
directly associated with the electricity consumption.
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
10 of 14
 
This also highlights that even though recovering more of the product and raw materials 
can increase the TCI, it has a lower negative influence on the process profitability than 
losing them. In addition, it is worth noting that the utility cost, as expected, has an insig-
nificant impact on the ROI as the current utility cost is $1.646 million per year, represent-
ing only 2.95% of the total product cost, which is due to the low-pressure requirement in 
the process compared to the conventional process, which is directly associated with the 
electricity consumption.  
 
Figure 7. Return on investment under various market variations of the economic factors. 
4.7. Effect of Reaction Temperature on the Process Profitability  
The temperature for reactor operation proposed by Al-Rabiah et al. [40,41] is in the 
range of (200–350) °C. The conducted sensitivity analysis has shown that it is appealing to 
increase the conversion and selectivity of the process. In the current study, the used tem-
perature is 300 °C. When the reactor temperature is increased to 350 °C, the conversion 
and selectivity are increased from 66% and 69.4% to 77.3% and 72.2%, respectively. Con-
sequently, less acetone is required, and more MIBK is produced. Nevertheless, this also 
increases the heating requirement needed for the feed stream as well as the reactor cooling 
system. In order to determine the optimum temperature in terms of profitability, the pro-
cess was simulated at 350 °C. All costs were determined in the same manner as previously 
-15
-10
-5
0
5
10
15
Percent Change %
0
10
20
30
40
50
60
ROI %
Raw Material
Product
Utilities
Fixed capital cost
Figure 7. Return on investment under various market variations of the economic factors.
4.7. Effect of Reaction Temperature on the Process Proﬁtability
The temperature for reactor operation proposed by Al-Rabiah et al. [40,41] is in the
range of (200–350) ◦C. The conducted sensitivity analysis has shown that it is appealing
to increase the conversion and selectivity of the process. In the current study, the used
temperature is 300 ◦C. When the reactor temperature is increased to 350 ◦C, the conver-
sion and selectivity are increased from 66% and 69.4% to 77.3% and 72.2%, respectively.
Consequently, less acetone is required, and more MIBK is produced. Nevertheless, this
also increases the heating requirement needed for the feed stream as well as the reactor
cooling system. In order to determine the optimum temperature in terms of proﬁtability,
the process was simulated at 350 ◦C. All costs were determined in the same manner as
previously done. Figure 8 shows that as the reactor temperature increases, the ﬁxed capital
investment decreases, which is due to the lower volume of the distillation column T-101 that
is needed to separate acetone from the process stream. In addition, the rest of the columns’
size remained almost the same as the production rate was ﬁxed. In addition, the cost of the
compressor decreased because the numbers of unreacted moles of acetone and hydrogen
were lower. On the other hand, the heating utility that is required to maintain the reactor
temperature was increased by about 10%. In addition, more heating utility was required
for E-102 because the minimum temperature approach was increased from 10 ◦C to 30 ◦C
to prevent a phase change prior to the compressor. It is worth noting that even though
the inlet temperature to E-105 was increased from 164 ◦C to 180 ◦C, the heat duty was
about 11% less due to the lower ﬂow rate entering the heat exchanger. The condenser and
reboiler heat loads of T-101 were also lower due to the lower amount of unreacted acetone.
An overall assessment of energy consumption is shown in Figure 8, which indicates that
increasing the temperature from 300 ◦C to 350 ◦C reduces the overall energy consumption
of the process. Furthermore, the ROI increased to 34.3%, and the payback period decreased
to 2 years.
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
11 of 14
 
cates that increasing the temperature from 300 °C to 350 °C reduces the overall energy 
consumption of the process. Furthermore, the ROI increased to 34.3%, and the payback 
period decreased to 2 years. 
In terms of profitability, the return on investment for the process when operating at 
350 °C is 35.1%/y, which is 18% higher while the net present worth has upsurged by 12%. 
Figure 9 depicts the cash flow diagram of both process conditions.  
 
Figure 8. A comparison between the effect of the eactor temperature on the FCI and the utility 
cost. 
Figure 8. A comparison between the effect of the eactor temperature on the FCI and the utility cost.
In terms of proﬁtability, the return on investment for the process when operating at
350 ◦C is 35.1%/y, which is 18% higher while the net present worth has upsurged by 12%.
Figure 9 depicts the cash ﬂow diagram of both process conditions.
Processes 2022, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW 
12 of 14 
 
 
Figure 9. The cumulative cash flow diagram for both reactor temperatures. 
5. Conclusions 
Methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) is a chemical intermediate and an important solvent. 
It is used in several important applications in the chemical market. There are several meth-
ods to produce MIBK, either by the three-step process or by the one-step liquid-phase 
reaction method, which is commercially preferred. However, these methods require very 
high pressure, which is expensive and energy consuming. In contrast, a promising nano-
Pd/nano-ZnCr2O4 catalyst was developed to produce MIBK in a one-step gas-phase reac-
tion under ambient pressure, overcoming the drawback of the conventional process. In 
this work, a novel process flowsheet has been developed and simulated. The developed 
process was heat integrated by matching the process streams to deliver the surplus heat 
to the heat deficit streams, resulting in a 12.6% reduction in the total energy demand. A 
comprehensive economic analysis of the developed process was conducted and has
Cumulative Cash Flow ($ million)
Figure 9. The cumulative cash ﬂow diagram for both reactor temperatures.
5. Conclusions
Methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) is a chemical intermediate and an important solvent.
It is used in several important applications in the chemical market. There are several
methods to produce MIBK, either by the three-step process or by the one-step liquid-
phase reaction method, which is commercially preferred. However, these methods require
very high pressure, which is expensive and energy consuming. In contrast, a promising
nano-Pd/nano-ZnCr2O4 catalyst was developed to produce MIBK in a one-step gas-phase
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
12 of 14
reaction under ambient pressure, overcoming the drawback of the conventional process. In
this work, a novel process ﬂowsheet has been developed and simulated. The developed
process was heat integrated by matching the process streams to deliver the surplus heat
to the heat deﬁcit streams, resulting in a 12.6% reduction in the total energy demand. A
comprehensive economic analysis of the developed process was conducted and has shown
that the process is highly proﬁtable with a return on investment (ROI) of 29.6% and a
payback period of 2.2 years. It is shown that when the process is operated at a temperature
of 350 ◦C, the economics improved, and the ROI increased to 34.3%.
6. Patents
US Patent No. 7,951,976, 31 May 2011, US Patent No. 8,101,805, 24 January 2012, EP
Patent No. 2,532,642 B1, 25 January 2017, EP Patent No. 2418017B1, 21 November 2018.
Author Contributions: Conceptualization, A.A.A.-R.; methodology, A.A.A.-R.; software, A.A.A.-R.
and R.R.A.; validation, A.A.A.-R. and R.R.A.; formal analysis, A.A.A.-R. and R.R.A.; investiga-
tion, A.A.A.-R. and R.R.A.; resources, A.A.A.-R. and A.A.B.; data curation, A.A.A.-R. and A.A.B.;
writing—original draft preparation, A.A.A.-R.; writing—review and editing, A.A.A.-R. and R.R.A.;
visualization, A.A.A.-R. and R.R.A.; supervision, A.A.A.-R.; project administration, A.A.A.-R. and
A.A.B.; funding acquisition, A.A.A.-R. and A.A.B. All authors have read and agreed to the published
version of the manuscript.
Funding: This research received no external funding.
Data Availability Statement: Not applicable.
Acknowledgments: This project was supported by King Saud University, Deanship of Scientiﬁc
Research, College of Engineering Research Center.
Conﬂicts of Interest: The authors declare no conﬂict of interest.
Abbreviations
Abbreviation
Deﬁnition
MIBK
Methyl Isobutyl Ketone
CAGR
Compound Annual Growth Rate
DAA
Diacetone alcohol
MO
Mesityl oxide
DIBK
Diiasobutyl ketone
M
Mesitylene
IPA
Isopropyl alcohol
W
Water
FCI
Fixed Capital Investment
TCI
Total capital investment
ROI
Return on investment
DCFRR
Discounted Cash Flow Rate of Return
References
1.
Kurbatova, M.V.; Cherentsova, M.I.; Raskulova, T.V.; Fereferov, M.Y.; Ryabtsov, A.Y. Low-temperature dewaxing of oils in the
presence of an individual solvent. Vestn. ANSTU 2018, 12, 69–72.
2.
Smirnova, A.; Grigor’eva, L.; Ostroukhov, N. Extraction of water-soluble phenols from shale-chemical process water. Solid Fuel
Chem. 2016, 50, 371–375. [CrossRef]
3.
Roy, C.B.; Awual, M.; Goto, M. Effect of inorganic salts on ternary equilibrium data of propionic acid-water-solvents systems. J.
Appl. Sci. 2007, 7, 1053. [CrossRef]
4.
Zhiyong, Z.; Wei, Q.; Weiyang, F.; Yigui, L. A study on stoichiometry of complexes of tributyl phosphate and methyl isobutyl
ketone with lithium in the presence of FeCl3. Chin. J. Chem. Eng. 2012, 20, 36–39.
5.
Xiang, W.; Liang, S.; Zhou, Z.; Qin, W.; Fei, W. Lithium recovery from salt lake brine by counter-current extraction using tributyl
phosphate/FeCl3 in methyl isobutyl ketone. Hydrometallurgy 2017, 171, 27–32. [CrossRef]
6.
Verma, R.K. Single-Step MIBK Process; IHS Markit: London, UK, 2019.
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
13 of 14
7.
Grosse, Y.; Baan, R.; Secretan-Lauby, B.; El Ghissassi, F.; Bouvard, V.; Benbrahim-Tallaa, L.; Guha, N.; Islami, F.; Galichet, L.;
Straif, K. Carcinogenicity of Chemicals in Industrial and Consumer Products, Food Contaminants and Flavourings, and Water Chlorination
Byproducts; Elsevier: Amsterdam, The Netherlands, 2011.
8.
Expert Market Research. “Global Methyl Isobutyl Ketone Market Report and Forecast 2022–2027.” Methyl Isobutyl Ketone
Market Report, Size, Share, Analysis 2022–2027, 2021. Available online: https://www.expertmarketresearch.com/reports/
methyl-isobutyl-ketone-market (accessed on 23 August 2022).
9.
Intelligence Mordor. “Methyl Isobutyl Ketone (MIBK) Market Size, Share: 2022–2027: Industry Analysis.” Methyl Isobutyl Ketone
(MIBK) Market Size, Share | 2022–2027 | Industry Analysis, 2021. Available online: https://www.mordorintelligence.com/
industry-reports/methyl-isobutyl-ketone-market (accessed on 23 August 2022).
10.
Rutala, A.W.; Weber, D.J. Guideline for Disinfection and Sterilization in Healthcare Facilities, 2008; CDC: Atlanta, GA, USA, 2008.
11.
Weissermel, K.; Arpe, H.-J. Industrial Organic Chemistry; John Wiley &amp; Sons: Hoboken, NJ, USA, 2008.
12.
Winter, F.; van Dillen, A.J.; de Jong, K.P. Single-stage liquid-phase synthesis of methyl isobutyl ketone under mild conditions. J.
Mol. Catal. A Chem. 2004, 219, 273–281. [CrossRef]
13.
Torres, G.; Apesteguia, C.R.; di Cosimo, J.I. One-step methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK) synthesis from 2-propanol: Catalyst and
reaction condition optimization. Appl. Catal. A Gen. 2007, 317, 161–170. [CrossRef]
14.
Lei, Z.; Li, J.; Li, C.; Chen, B. Improvement of separation process of synthesizing MIBK by the isopropanol one-step method.
Korean J. Chem. Eng. 2006, 23, 264–270. [CrossRef]
15.
Cosimo, J.; Torres, G.; Apesteguıa, C. One-step MIBK synthesis: A new process from 2-propanol. J. Catal. 2002, 208, 114–123.
[CrossRef]
16.
Mattos, V.L.; Noronha, F.B.; Monteiro, J.L.F. Bifunctional metal/base catalysts (Pt/X) for the direct synthesis of MIBK from
acetone. J. Catal. 2002, 209, 166–176. [CrossRef]
17.
Mayevskiy, M.; Frolkova, A.; Frolkova, A. Separation and puriﬁcation of methyl isobutyl ketone from acetone + isopropanol
+ water + methyl isobutyl ketone + methyl isobutyl carbinol + diisobutyl ketone mixture. ACS Omega 2020, 5, 25365–25370.
[CrossRef] [PubMed]
18.
Bagabas, A.A.; Mokhtar, M.; Akhmedov, V.; Narasimharao, K.; Basahel, S.N.; Al-Rabiah, A. Ru–C–ZnO Composite Catalysts for
the Synthesis of Methyl Isobutyl Ketone via Single Step Gas Phase Acetone Self-Condensation. Catal. Lett. 2014, 144, 1278–1288.
[CrossRef]
19.
Gamman, J.J.; Jackson, S.D.; Wigzell, F.A. Synthesis of methyl isobutyl ketone over Pd/MgO/SiO2. Ind. Eng. Chem. Res. 2010, 49,
8439–8443. [CrossRef]
20.
Bagabas, A.A.; Akhmedov, V.M.; Al-Rabiah, A.; Mostafa, M.M.M. Synthesizing and Utilizing Novel Nano Crystalline Zinc
Chromate Supported Nano Palladium Catalyst. U.S. Patent US 7,951,976, 31 May 2011.
21.
Kelkar, V.V.; Vaibhav, V.; Lionel, K.; O’Young, C.; Wibowo, M.; Kelkar, H.; Chung, C. Two-Step System and Method for the
Production of Methyl Isobutyl Ketone. U.S. Patent US 9120734B2, September 2015.
22.
Shylesh, S.; Hanna, D.; Gomes, J.; Canlas, C.G.; Head-Gordon, M.; Bell, A.T. The Role of Hydroxyl Group Acidity on the Activity
of Silica-Supported Secondary Amines for the Self-Condensation of n-Butanal. ChemSusChem 2015, 8, 466–472. [CrossRef]
[PubMed]
23.
Talwalkar, S.; Mahajani, S. Synthesis of methyl isobutyl ketone from acetone over metal-doped ion exchange resin catalyst. Appl.
Catal. A Gen. 2006, 302, 140–148. [CrossRef]
24.
Nicol, W.; du Toit, E.L. One-step methyl isobutyl ketone synthesis from acetone and hydrogen using Amberlyst®CH28. Chem.
Eng. Process. Process Intensif. 2004, 43, 1539–1545. [CrossRef]
25.
Zhang, S.; Wu, P.; Yang, L.; Zhou, Y.; Zhong, H. An efﬁcient bifunctional catalyst of TiO2 coating and supported Pd on cordierite
for one-pot synthesis of MIBK from acetone. Catal. Commun. 2015, 71, 61–64. [CrossRef]
26.
Rao, P.V.R.; Kumar, V.P.; Rao, G.S.; Chary, K.V. Vapor phase selective hydrogenation of acetone to methyl isobutyl ketone (MIBK)
over Ni/CeO2 catalysts. Catal. Sci. Technol. 2012, 2, 1665–1673. [CrossRef]
27.
Nikolopoulos, A.; Jang, B.-L.; Spivey, J. Acetone condensation and selective hydrogenation to MIBK on Pd and Pt hydrotalcite-
derived MgAl mixed oxide catalysts. Appl. Catal. A Gen. 2005, 296, 128–136. [CrossRef]
28.
Chen, Y.; Hwang, C.; Liaw, C. One-step synthesis of methyl isobutyl ketone from acetone with calcined Mg/Al hydrotalcite-
supported palladium or nickel catalysts. Appl. Catal. A Gen. 1998, 169, 207–214. [CrossRef]
29.
Ho, C.R.; Zheng, S.; Shylesh, S.; Bell, A.T. The mechanism and kinetics of methyl isobutyl ketone synthesis from acetone over
ion-exchanged hydroxyapatite. J. Catal. 2018, 365, 174–183. [CrossRef]
30.
Schmitt, K.; Disteldorf, J.; Flakus, W.; Hubel, W. Process for preparing methyl isobutyl ketone and catalyst. U.S. Patent US
3,953,517, April 1976.
31.
Rase, H.F. Handbook of Commercial Catalysts: Heterogeneous Catalysts; CRC Press: Boca Raton, FL, USA, 2000.
32.
Kozhevnikova, F.E.; Kozhevnikov, I.V. One-step synthesis of methyl isobutyl ketone from acetone catalysed by Pd supported on
ZnII–CrIII mixed oxide. J. Catal. 2006, 238, 286–292. [CrossRef]
33.
Guisnet, M. Heterogeneous catalysis and ﬁne chemicals. In International Symposium on Heterogeneous Catalysis and Fine Chemicals
(1988: Poitiers, France); Distributors for the US and Canada; Elsevier Science Pub. Co.: Amsterdam, The Netherlands, 1988.
34.
Zhu, Q.; Duan, H.; Lin, B.; Zhu, Y.; Hu, Y.; Zhou, Y. Higher Acetone Conversion Obtained Over a TiO2–Pd Bifunctional Catalyst
for Liquid-Phase Synthesis of Methyl Isobutyl Ketone: The Role of Al2O3 Support. Catal. Lett. 2019, 149, 2636–2644. [CrossRef]
Processes 2022, 10, 1992
14 of 14
35.
Lin, B.; Xu, F.; Hu, Y.; Du, X.; Zou, Y.; Xie, H.; Wang, K.; Zhou, Y. An efﬁcient multifunctional catalyst for one-pot synthesis of
methyl isobutyl ketone: Phosphor-doped h-BN with adjustable acid-base property as support. Catal. Commun. 2021, 150, 106276.
[CrossRef]
36.
Duan, H.; Wang, Z.; Cui, L.; Lin, B.; Zhou, Y. Stability Investigation of a Supported TiO2–Pd Bifunctional Catalyst over the
One-Pot Liquid-Phase Synthesis of Methyl Isobutyl Ketone from Acetone and H2. Ind. Eng. Chem. Res. 2018, 57, 12358–12366.
[CrossRef]
37.
Zhu, Q.; Dai, H. Exposure Assessment of Emerging Chemicals and Novel Screening Strategies. In Emerging Chemicals and Human
Health; Springer: Berlin, Germany, 2019; pp. 9–26.
38.
Zhu, Y.; Lin, B.; Hu, Y.; Cai, Z.; Xie, H.; Wang, K.; Zhou, Y. Enhanced stability of Pd/SPS catalyst over the one-pot liquid-phase
synthesis of methyl isobutyl ketone by adding GO. Mol. Catal. 2019, 478, 110609. [CrossRef]
39.
Liu, M.; Liu, G.; Zhou, Y.; Han, K.; Ye, H. Sulfonated graphene oxide supported Pd bifunctional catalyst for one-pot synthesis of
methyl isobutyl ketone from acetone with high conversion and selectivity. J. Mol. Catal. A Chem. 2015, 408, 85–90. [CrossRef]
40.
Al-Rabiah, A.A.; Bagabas, A.A.; Malik, A.V. Low Pressure One-Step Gas-Phase Process for Production of Methyl Isobutyl Ketone.
U.S. Patent US 8,101,805, 24 January 2012.
41.
Al-Rabiah, A.A.; Bagabas, A.A.; Akhmedov, V.M. Low Pressure One-Step Gas-Phase Process for Production of Methyl Isobutyl
Ketone. E.P. Patent E.P. 2,532,642 B1, 25 January 2017.
42.
Peters, M.; Timmerhaus, K.; West, R. Plant Design and Economics for Chemical Engineers, 5th ed.; McGraw Hill: New York, NY, USA,
2016.
43.
Alexandre, C.D. Chapter 19—Economic Evaluation of Projects. In Computer Aided Chemical Engineering; Elsevier: Amsterdam, The
Netherlands, 2014; Volume 35, pp. 717–755.
44.
Thomas, M. Chemical Engineering Plant Cost Index. In Chemical Engineering; The U.S. Department of Labor’s Bureau of Labor
Statistics: Washington, DC, USA, 2022.
45.
Chemanalyst. Chemical Price Analysis, Chemical Latest Prices | ChemAnalyst. 2022. Available online: https://www.
chemanalyst.com/Pricing/Pricingoverview (accessed on 23 August 2022).
46.
Turton, R.; Bailie, R.C.; Whiting, W.B.; Shaeiwitz, J.A. Analysis, Synthesis, and Design of Chemical Processes, 5th ed.; Prentice Hall:
Hoboken, NJ, USA, 2018.
47.
Hong, S.C.; Musso, T.J. Simons Oil-Price Shocks and the Chemical Industry: Preparing for a Volatile Environment; McKinsey and
Company: Atlanta, GA, USA, 2015.
48.
Knight, P. Oil and Gas Market Volatile, Petrochemical Market May Follow Suit If Invasion Prolongs; University of California Press:
Berkley, CA, USA, 2022.
</pdf_text>